a species poised between gaining the stars and losing the planet we call home.
تأرجح البشرية بين كسب النجوم وفقدان الكوكب الذي نسميه الوطن.
Even in just the past few years, we've greatly expanded
حتى في السنوات القليلة الماضية، توسّعت بشكل كبير
our knowledge of how Earth fits within the context of our universe.
معرفتنا بكيفية تناسب الأرض في سياق كوننا.
NASA's Kepler mission has discovered
اكتشفت بعثة كبلرالتابع لوكالة ناسا
thousands of potential planets around other stars,
الآلاف من الكواكب المحتملة حول النجوم الأخرى،
indicating that Earth is but one of billions of planets in our galaxy.
مشيرة إلى أن الأرض ليست سوى واحدة من مليارات الكواكب في مجرتنا.
Kepler is a space telescope
كبلر هو تلسكوب فضائي
that measures the subtle dimming of stars as planets pass in front of them,
يقيس الظلام الباهت للنجوم، عندما تمر الكواكب أمامهم،
blocking just a little bit of that light from reaching us.
يحجب قليلًا من الضوء من الوصول إلينا.
Kepler's data reveals planets' sizes
تكشف بيانات كبلر أحجام الكواكب
as well as their distance from their parent star.
وكذلك بُعدها عن النجم الأم لكل منها.
Together, this helps us understand whether these planets are small and rocky,
تساعدنا هذه البيانات مجتمعة على فهم ما إذا كانت هذه الكواكب صغيرة وصخرية،
like the terrestrial planets in our own Solar System,
مثل الكواكب الأرضية في نظامنا الشمسي،
and also how much light they receive from their parent sun.
وأيضًا كمية الضوء التي تستقبلها من الشمس الأم.
In turn, this provides clues as to whether these planets that we discover
في المقابل، يُوفر هذا أدلة فيما إذا كانت هذه الكواكب التي نكتشفها
might be habitable or not.
صالحة للسكن أم لا.
Unfortunately, at the same time as we're discovering this treasure trove
لسوء الحظ، في نفس الوقت الذي نكتشف فيه هذا الكنز الدفين
of potentially habitable worlds,
للعوالم المحتمل السكن فيها،
our own planet is sagging under the weight of humanity.
يتراجع كوكبنا تحت وطأة الإنسانية.
2014 was the hottest year on record.
كان 2014 هو الأكثر حرارة على الاطلاق.
Glaciers and sea ice that have been with us for millennia
الأنهار الجليدية والجليد البحري التي كانت معنا منذ الآلاف السنين
are now disappearing in a matter of decades.
تختفي الآن في غضون عقود.
These planetary-scale environmental changes that we have set in motion
هذه التغيرات البيئية على المستوى الكوكبي التي وضعناها في الحركة
are rapidly outpacing our ability to alter their course.
تفوق سرعتها قدرتنا على تغيير مسارها.
But I'm not a climate scientist, I'm an astronomer.
لست عالمة في المناخ أنا عالمة فلك.
I study planetary habitability as influenced by stars
أدرس الكواكب واحتمالية السكن فيها وتأثرها بالنجوم
with the hopes of finding the places in the universe
مع الآمال في العثور على أماكن في الكون
where we might discover life beyond our own planet.
خارج كوكبنا يمكن أن نكتشف بها حياة.
You could say that I look for choice alien real estate.
يُمكنكم القول أنني أبحث عن عقار في الفضاء.
Now, as somebody who is deeply embedded in the search for life in the universe,
حاليًا، كشخص متعمق في البحث عن حياة في الكون،
I can tell you that the more you look for planets like Earth,
أستطيع أن أقول لكم أنه كلما زاد بحثكم عن كواكب تشبه الأرض،
the more you appreciate our own planet itself.
زاد تقديركم لكوكبنا نفسه.
Each one of these new worlds invites a comparison
ويثير كل من هذه العوالم الجديدة مقارنة
between the newly discovered planet and the planets we know best:
بين الكواكب المكتشفة حديثًا والكواكب التي نعرفها جيدًا.
those of our own Solar System.
تلك المتواجدة في مجموعتنا الشمسية.
Consider our neighbor, Mars.
أنظر إلى جارنا المريخ.
Mars is small and rocky, and though it's a bit far from the Sun,
المريخ صغير وصخري، وعلى الرغم من أنه بعيد قليلًا عن الشمس،
it might be considered a potentially habitable world
إلا إنه قد يعتبر مكان يُحتمل السكن فيه
if found by a mission like Kepler.
إذا وُجد من قبل بعثة مثل كبلر.
Indeed, it's possible that Mars was habitable in the past,
في الواقع، من المحتمل أن المريخ كان مكان صالحًا للسكن في الماضي،
and in part, this is why we study Mars so much.
ولهذا السبب نحن ندرسُ المريخ كثيرًا.
Our rovers, like Curiosity, crawl across its surface,
عرباتنا المتجولة مثل كيوريوسيتي روفر تمسح سطح المريخ،
scratching for clues as to the origins of life as we know it.
تحفر بحثًا عن أدلة لأصول الحياة كما نعرفها.
Orbiters like the MAVEN mission sample the Martian atmosphere,
المسابير الفضائية مثل بعثة مافن تجمعُ عينات من الغلاف الجوي للمريخ،
trying to understand how Mars might have lost its past habitability.
في محاولة لسبب فناء الحياة على المريخ
Private spaceflight companies now offer not just a short trip to near space
تقدم شركات الطيران الفضائي الآن ليس مجرد رحلة قصيرة إلى الفضاء القريب
but the tantalizing possibility of living our lives on Mars.
لكن الاحتمالية المؤلمة لنعيش حياتنا على كوكب المريخ.
But though these Martian vistas
لكن على الرغم من أنّ آفاق المريخ
resemble the deserts of our own home world,
تشبه صحاري عالمنا،
places that are tied in our imagination to ideas about pioneering and frontiers,
والأماكن التي ترتبط في خيالنا بالأفكار حول الريادة والحدود،
compared to Earth
مقارنة مع الأرض
Mars is a pretty terrible place to live.
المريخ هو مكان رهيب جدًا للعيش فيه.
Consider the extent to which we have not colonized
أنظر إلى مدى هجرنا
the deserts of our own planet,
لصحاري كوكبنا،
places that are lush by comparison with Mars.
الأماكن الخصبة بالمقارنة مع المريخ.
Even in the driest, highest places on Earth,
حتى في الأماكن الأكثر جفافًا، وعلوًا على الأرض،
the air is sweet and thick with oxygen
فالهواء لطيف ومشبع بالأكسجين
exhaled from thousands of miles away by our rainforests.
المنبعث من على بعد آلاف الأميال عن طريق الغابات المطيرة.
I worry -- I worry that this excitement about colonizing Mars and other planets
أنا قلقة -- قلقة من أنّ هذا الحماس حول استعمار المريخ والكواكب الأخرى
carries with it a long, dark shadow:
يحمل في طياته طيف قاتم طويل:
the implication and belief by some
الافتراض الضمني والاعتقاد من قبل البعض
that Mars will be there to save us from the self-inflicted destruction
بأن المريخ سيكون هناك لينقذنا من إلحاق التدمير الذاتي
of the only truly habitable planet we know of, the Earth.
للكوكب الوحيد الصالح للسكن حقًا" وهو "الأرض" التي نعرفها.
As much as I love interplanetary exploration,
بقدر ما أحب استكشاف الكواكب،
I deeply disagree with this idea.
فإنني أختلف بشدة مع هذه الفكرة.
There are many excellent reasons to go to Mars,
هناك العديد من الأسباب النبيلة للذهاب إلى المريخ،
but for anyone to tell you that Mars will be there to back up humanity
ولكن أي شخص يخبركم بأن المريخ سوف يكون البديل المنقذ للبشرية
is like the captain of the Titanic telling you that the real party
فهو في ذلك يشبه قبطان تايتانيك الذي يخبركم أن الحفلة الحقيقية
is happening later on the lifeboats.
ستحدثُ لاحقًا على قوارب النجاة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
But the goals of interplanetary exploration and planetary preservation
لكن أهداف الاستكشاف والحفاظ على الكواكب
are not opposed to one another.
لا تتعارض مع بعضها البعض.
No, they're in fact two sides of the same goal:
لا، إنها في الواقع وجهين لنفس الهدف:
to understand, preserve and improve life into the future.
فهي لفهم وصيانة وتحسين الحياة في المستقبل.
The extreme environments of our own world are alien vistas.
لأن البيئات القاسية لعالمنا الخاص هي آفاق غريبة دخيلة.
They're just closer to home.
هي فقط قريبة من الوطن "الأرض".
If we can understand how to create and maintain habitable spaces
إذا استطعنا فهم كيفية إنشاء المساحات الصالحة للسكن والحفاظ عليها
out of hostile, inhospitable spaces here on Earth,
خارج المساحات الوعرة المعادية البعيدة هنا على الأرض،
perhaps we can meet the needs of both preserving our own environment
فلربما يمكننا تلبية الاحتياجات لكل من المحافظة على بيئتنا الخاصة
and moving beyond it.
والتحرك أبعد من ذلك.
I leave you with a final thought experiment:
أترككم مع تجربة فكرية أخيرة:
Fermi's paradox.
مفارقة فيرمي.
Many years ago, the physicist Enrico Fermi asked that, given the fact
منذ سنوات عديدة، سأل الفيزيائي انريكو فيرمي، نظرًا للحقيقة المزعومة
that our universe has been around for a very long time
أن كوننا قد كان حولنا لفترة طويلة جدًا
and we expect that there are many planets within it,
ونحن نتوقع أن هناك العديد من الكواكب ضمن حدوده،
we should have found evidence for alien life by now.
كان ينبغي علينا العثور على أدلة لوجود الكائنات الفضائية الآن.
So where are they?
فأين هم؟
Well, one possible solution to Fermi's paradox
حسنًا، الحل الممكن الوحيد لمفارقة فيرمي
is that, as civilizations become technologically advanced enough
هي أنه كلما أضحت الحضارات متقدمة تكنولوجيًا بما في الكفاية
to consider living amongst the stars,
للنظر في العيش بين النجوم،
they lose sight of how important it is
يغيب عن بالها كم هو مهم
to safeguard the home worlds that fostered that advancement to begin with.
المحافظة على حضاراتنا التي تعزز هذا التقدم بادئ ذي بدء.
It is hubris to believe that interplanetary colonization alone
فمن الغطرسة الاعتقاد أن استعمار الكواكب وحدها
will save us from ourselves,
سينقدنا من أنفسنا،
but planetary preservation and interplanetary exploration
لكن الاستكشاف والحفاظ على الكواكب
can work together.
يُمكن أن تعمل سويًا.
If we truly believe in our ability
إذا آمنّا حقًا بقدرتنا
to bend the hostile environments of Mars for human habitation,
لتحمل بيئات المريخ الوعرة المعادية للسكن البشري،
then we should be able to surmount the far easier task of preserving
إذًا يجب أن نكون قادرون على التغلب على المهمة الأسهل بكثير بشأن الحفاظ
the habitability of the Earth.
على السكن والعيش في الأرض.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)